[SPEAKER_01]: There's a sutta in the Sutta Nipātā called Sāla Sutta, the Arrow.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it basically speaks about mortality, death and loss, grieving.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, let's go through a few verses and see where we go from there.
[SPEAKER_01]: The first verse, it says, signless and unpredictable is the life of mortals here, difficult and limited and conjoined with suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, verse 15, which relates this, for in whatever way they conceive, it becomes otherwise.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of such a sort is the nature of separation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I like this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Signless and unpredictable is the life of mortals.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's signless.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unpredictable.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I was just thinking that...
[SPEAKER_01]: That emphasis, people don't emphasize that.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't even see that, that it's unpredictable.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, what they see is that it's predictable.
[SPEAKER_01]: I won't...
[SPEAKER_01]: I probably won't die today.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything's going well.
[SPEAKER_01]: I've got things to do tomorrow.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things...
[SPEAKER_01]: I feel okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no danger here.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not true.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, that is the sign that one lives with.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like a fantasy.
[SPEAKER_01]: That sign helps you feel, in a way, that things are in control.
[SPEAKER_01]: To some degree, you know you've got your plans for tomorrow and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's not a definite thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not predictable.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, it's just about coming back, trying to see that that nature, that there is no sign for...
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing in your experience, actually, that you can rely on, that proves that you're going to be here tomorrow.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I'm healthy now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's a good chance I will still be here tomorrow.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, even that means... doesn't mean that you're not going to die in the next breath.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, relying on that, if I rely on this... if I rely on the... or cultivate that perception of next breath, I could die, or I cultivate the perception of, no, tomorrow I might still be here.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, when things... if I cultivate the latter, I will probably still be here.
[SPEAKER_01]: When things don't go according to my expectations, it's going to be a big, massive slap in the face.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like... well, yeah, I mean, that's the... that's kind of the outcome of your practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if somebody thinks they can just start contemplating those levels now, it's not going to work.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just... well, it might... yeah, it's gonna either be too much, in terms of, like, anxiety and fear that will arise on account of it, or it will be something way too abstract that they will not be able to sustain, and it's just gonna become a mechanical kind of mantra-like repetition, the, oh, yeah, my next breath, and be here now, and whatnot, but none of that carries the weight anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, instead of trying to force those, as I said,
[SPEAKER_00]: Technically, well, factually, kind of higher or more advanced ways of contemplation, you need to remove everything that's preventing those types of contemplation to be concrete for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, everything that's in the way of you contemplating your experience rightly, here and now, needs to be addressed first.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, again, it's like the simile of purifying the gold, like you're focusing on this refined, kind of precise removal of the very fine impurities, you know, the ones at the deepest level, while the whole gold is still swimming in, like, mud and crap and who knows what.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's simply not going to work.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I think, first and foremost, practically, a person needs to recognize that it doesn't matter how much you think you're living in the present moment and what type of effort, you know, you're putting in.
[SPEAKER_00]: For as long as you're not a sotāpanna, your entire experience is still lived by a... fundamentally by a great deal of projections, through projections.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything you do, you think, you believe, you set yourself, it's a projection.
[SPEAKER_00]: Including discovering the dhamma I wanted to practice becomes another projection.
[SPEAKER_00]: But always it's a projection that carries a potential to turn against itself and reveal the nature of projections.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you stop living through these conceivings of things that are fundamentally otherwise.
[SPEAKER_00]: Projections or perversions, whatever Sutta calls them, perversions, intoxications, whichever way you want to describe it, that needs to be undone first, for all these correct contemplations of death and the next breath and ānāpānasati and all this, to actually start making sense and do the work it's supposed to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, that will become another projection, another perversion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how do you undo perversions?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, by recognizing the whole description of the gradual training, what it starts with, and to start developing that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you cannot, factually, you cannot...
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter how much effort you use with tweezers to purify the, like, subtle impurities from gold.
[SPEAKER_00]: If the whole liquid is still floating in mud, you're factually making no difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the little experiences and insights you might have on account of...
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever effort you made towards understanding dhamma and going on a retreat and stuff, if what you go back to is the basis of sensuality, ill-will, not keeping the precepts only occasionally or not fully purifying, not developing and not seeing the fault in the slightest, not seeing the danger in the slightest fault and all of that, if you'd have not even developed that, no amount of your work and insights make any difference, because, again, you go back into the same dirt, same mud, which which nullifies anything, anything that you would have cleaned, supposedly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anyway, it's like you remind me that the danger of contemplating death and anicca, as I'm saying, while not having given up sensual activities or calmed your mind, or no precepts, means that that's what you go back to.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's almost guaranteed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you don't, like, you wouldn't even go back.
[SPEAKER_00]: You never leave it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You never leave, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, contemplating these things, we're just going to create even more of that
[SPEAKER_00]: Tension, an artificial kind of tension and pressure, that's not because of the contemplation, but because of the things you're still holding dear and refusing to let go of, that are now being threatened by the contemplation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, some degree of contemplation, some degree of divine messengers can wake a person up from that sort of mindless oblivion, but, like,
[SPEAKER_00]: Fundamentally, if you really want to transcend it, and step out of it, and free yourself from it, you need to start tailoring your actions, by body, speech, and mind, to match that withdrawal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just believe that, oh, I don't have to give these things up.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't have to make the effort and say no to things first, things of sensual nature, acting out of ill will, distraction that I choose, and somehow this contemplation will do that for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just going to create more and more tension, and basically,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's probably going to result in one new type of cover-up or the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like that... have a wild animal and then you... instead of training it, you know, to calm down first, you show it death and you... like these things that it doesn't want to see, that it's scared.
[SPEAKER_00]: While it's still wild, while it can still attack you, while it can still go back into wilderness and make things even worse.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like, when you're trying to catch a wild animal, what do you do?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you go full force, loud, with a whip, screaming in its face, and expect it to not run away from you, or attack you in defense?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or do you try to, like, stealth mode, come around, set up a barrier, a fence, that the animal doesn't even know about, until it tries to escape, and then it finds the new walls around it?
[SPEAKER_00]: You already know the answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you think you can just go into these contemplations or perceptions while the animal still has the free roam, well, it's gonna either attack you, as I said, if you startle it, or run away from you and then be impossible to catch.
[SPEAKER_00]: Good luck stopping your behavior then.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, obviously, in some way, it's... even for a person who's not keeping the precepts,
[SPEAKER_01]: Not restraint at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just getting a divine messenger of, oh, you know, you got cancer now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can wake them and be like, oh, how am I living my life?
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, it's like a shock.
[SPEAKER_01]: That doesn't necessarily make them do worse things, but that can help them, like, reflect on the whole of their life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why am I doing this?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or do worse things.
[SPEAKER_01]: It depends on the person.
[SPEAKER_00]: If they had some initial wisdom or some self-reflection, some transparency, yes, they would probably use that in a more beneficial manner.
[SPEAKER_00]: But more often than not, people would kind of just try to double down and get the most of what they can get until it's too late.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's probably the most common reaction.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, the question, the point is not, like, to never think about these things, because it's dangerous or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Think about it, but recognize that the first thing comes first.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, think about it, if you need an inspiration as to why to stick to the precepts, why to continue training in that, why to endure the states of the mind that try to pressure you to act out and not act out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Remind yourself of, well, I'm dealing with, obviously,
[SPEAKER_00]: fundamental existential danger that I could actually genuinely escape if I develop this.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can genuinely free myself from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But don't think that simply through, like, forcing or going through these contemplations, the work of the gradual training can be sort of, you know, done for you by these practices.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, that's just magical thinking, basically, and believing in the connections when they're not there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the danger of contemplation, of death, even mindfulness of the body, without... Yeah, even the subha... And honesty, self-honesty.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, without the fence around your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Without the fence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Without the impenetrable fence of virtue having been well established beforehand, as the suttas would say, for a long time.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just on the some other verses that I found interesting, these verse 10, 11 and 12, says, if the one lamenting would derive any benefit, and if the one crying would derive any benefit, then the wise one would do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: For not by weeping or by grief does one obtain peace of mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: More arises, more suffering arises, and the body is injured, harmed through that lamenting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Lean and discolored he becomes, self-harming.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not by that are the departed protected.
[SPEAKER_01]: Useless is crying.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this is about, you know, the grief and the trap of like this, well, performativeness of grief, grieving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like you... and there's that whole...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, and the point is, you perform it for yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not necessarily performing it for others.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you might be... Like, genuine grief is something you do for yourself, to yourself, to not have to deal with the mind that's affected by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it gets worse.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just aggravates the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Agitating yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, as you just said, not by that are the departed protected.
[SPEAKER_01]: They are not helped by your grief.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not done for them.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: The person's gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's that idea of seven stages of grief that one must go through.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if you're not going through it,
[SPEAKER_01]: In a way, it's like, yeah, there's...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think there's acceptance of what has happened.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's like you're still grieving.
[SPEAKER_01]: But this particular sutta, and I think it says it later on, but anyway, we might get to that, that grief must be just blown away.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no... that is... there's no benefit in doing... Yeah, but obviously, you can't just blow it away.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a state of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the mind that hasn't still overcome the animal, that hasn't been fully tamed, hasn't been withdrawn from dependencies on sense objects or possessions, it will grieve.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's more like, do you take that grief at face value and go with it and allow it to overwhelm you?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or are you able to maintain perspective in face of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how the animal learns to calm and not give in to that, because you're not fueling it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's, yeah, it's not just something you could just switch off.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But again, it's like, if one is, what we just spoke about as well, if one is grieving, it's a kind of sign that... Well, that there's still work to be done.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and it was a surprise to you that you lost this thing, a complete, like, you didn't consider that thing, to the degree that you're grieving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or you haven't been considering it sufficiently enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's... For it to sink in, for it... for the animal to understand.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, it's inevitable.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can say to yourself it's inevitable, but it doesn't really sink down for the mind to hear it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, why this is wrong?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is this happening to me?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's like a frequent recollection of those things is necessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not just like, oh, yeah, I know that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you know that, and now keep, keep, keep reminding yourself of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Until really, you can't forget.
[SPEAKER_00]: The animal can't forget it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's always there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's always obvious.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, he won't be able to grieve amidst the grieving circumstances.
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't be able to suffer amidst not getting what it wants or losing what it wants.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the degree of grief is the degree of blindness to reality, basically, to the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: The things that you hold dear are not yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, the degree of grief reveals the degree of projection that still needs to be undone.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then that, obviously, that's... that grieving is a kind of... you need to do it to honor the people.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but those are like silly worldly views, basically, have not much to do with the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, and there's this other point I was thinking about, that crying almost... the idea that crying and grieving about the loss is kind of healing for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's very common.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you get it out, you know?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cry it out, and then you feel better.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it goes hand in hand with the view of that desire is something you need to act out of, because you don't make you feel better.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you only feel better, so to speak, because you're just absolutely exhausted.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now things have changed, you feel different.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You feel exhausted.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then the pain, there's still... when you start remembering, when you get your energy back, you're grieving again.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it doesn't heal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, exactly same like the desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's exactly the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: You stop wanting what you got, because you just scratched it, so it went numb.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not because you healed it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, give it some time, and it's gonna start itching again.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you haven't really changed anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you have changed.
[SPEAKER_00]: You made things worse.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because now you need to scratch deeper and deeper.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cry harder and harder, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or distract yourself harder and harder, so that it doesn't come up the way it comes up.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's always going to catch you, it's always going to surprise you at some point, and you know that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, crying, grieving is a distraction to this pain that you feel.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a cover-up, because you don't want to have to deal with the pressure and the weight of the pain of your attachment that now got violated by the circumstances.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yeah, so not grieving, and if you actually want to... Not giving in to grief is how you can then, with obviously right training, not just like, oh, I won't do this.
[SPEAKER_00]: But containing your mind that wants to give in to that direction, not allowing it, not acting out of it, like with everything else, the principles of the training do not change, is how eventually the mind will go beyond grief, and it won't be able to grieve, because what is there to grieve, really?
[SPEAKER_00]: When every projection, every acquisition, every attachment has been seen for what it is, has been let go of truly, there is no more basis for any grief or perversion to come out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, just a few more verses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Verse 18.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just as one would extinguish a blazing shelter with water, thus also the firm one, possessing wisdom, the learned, skillful man would blow away quickly arisen grief, like the wind a tuft of cotton.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like the simile of the heating up the pan.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have a cold iron pan and you drop water on it or something and it will just sit there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not gonna... it's not gonna evaporate.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will sit there and, you know, eventually turn into a swamp.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't just blow away the water directly, but you heat up the pan.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the right practice, is heating up the pan, the right things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whatever falls on it, it will evaporate instantly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not because you caught it in a second, but because the pan is hot enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when people don't understand that order of training, reading the suttas like that would sound as if, like, I catch things in a millisecond as they arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thing comes, and I instantly deal with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like whack-a-mole.
[SPEAKER_00]: Instantly.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's no.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: You heat up the mind, and how quickly things disappear reveals not how quickly you caught it, but how hot the mind was, how correctly heated up it was.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's same with the grief.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will be blown away immediately, dispelled, because of the underlying heat of the right training and the gradual training and the development.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't go around hunting things or waiting for them to come, so that you can instantly act and react and show your reflexes.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You heat up the mind and then you're not worried about any water that comes on it, because you know it cannot stay there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's going to evaporate instantly, the hotter it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if it gets really, really hot, it can't even land on it anymore, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, not taking things as mind or seeing... always seeing that, not...
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, obviously, precepts, restraint, not adding out a craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can be sure that if my mind has diminished this aversion, lust and ignoring nature of things... Yeah, willfully ignoring certain aspects.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't have to, like, preemptively imagine things happening before I can deal with them.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like I am now dealing with everything that could possibly happen, that could ever be painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any loss, I'm dealing with it now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Before it has occurred.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when it occurs, it's like...
[SPEAKER_01]: As you're saying, just evaporated.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you will, you can, and you will develop confidence in that recognition.
[SPEAKER_00]: If the mind is trained rightly, as I said, you don't need to go and test.
[SPEAKER_00]: And throw water at it to see.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, water will come one way or the other.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by that point, you would have learned where the practice is, where the emphasis is, what you should be heating up, what you should kind of refrain from trying to react and manage.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, even if, like, you don't know what would happen, you know that whatever were to happen,
[SPEAKER_00]: It has to go through the same, as I said.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will follow the same steps, the same procedure of falling onto the mind, onto the pan that's now been heated, and you're confident in its heat, so you wouldn't be afraid of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's like the lion's roar.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, lion does not... he's not... lion is not afraid in the jungle because he has an inventory of everybody that... who's there, who comes and goes, and their capacities and what they can do to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's not afraid because he doesn't... he knows that whatever it is, it cannot be a danger to me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever, whoever.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the confidence.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, you know, walks around like a king of the jungle and stuff like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, so, when you have confidence in the right training, the gradual training that you develop rightly, the properly, sufficiently, suitably heated pan,
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to keep an inventory of all the possibilities and everything that could come.
[SPEAKER_00]: And how about this?
[SPEAKER_00]: And how about that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you know that whatever comes, has to come through this entrance that's been sufficiently, correctly developed, hot, and it will be scorched away, basically, without your any effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your effort has been made beforehand of heating it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, you don't need to be quickly wiping the drops of water that fell on it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just need to make sure that you don't, through your own choices and negligence, cool down the pan.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that tapas, that actual...
[SPEAKER_00]: The actual, yes, the actual burning of the defilements, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the middle way.
[SPEAKER_01]: It burns away everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, and like the foremost of those tapas practices was khanti, patient endurance, or enduring things on the right level, as we say.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think one of the last verses, 19 and 20, one who seeks their own happiness would pluck out their own dart, the wailing and moaning, the sad and sadness inside, with dart plucked out unattached, having found peace of mind, overcoming all sorrow, one is sorrowless and quenched.
[SPEAKER_00]: Self-explanatory.